The field of
information retrieval has
been around for a while as
a subfield of
natural language processing,
and there's many approaches to
improving the relevancy of query results.
But what's new is we have powerful
large language models, and we
can use those to augment and enhance the
queries that we send
to our vector-based retrieval system
to get better
results.
Let's take a look.
So the first type of query expansion we're
going to talk about is called
expansion with generated
answers.
Typically the way that this works
is you take your query and
you pass it over to an
LLM which you prompt to generate
a hypothetical or
imagined answer to your query and
then you concatenate
your query with the imagined answer
and use that as the new
query which you pass to your
retrieval system or vector database.
Then you return your
query results as normal. Let's
take a look at how
this works in practice.
So the first thing that we're
going to do is once
again and grab all the
utilities that we need.
And we're going to load
everything we need from Chrome and
create our embedding function.
And we're going to set up
our OpenAI client again, because
we'll be using the LLM.
And once again,
to help with visualization, we're
going to use UMAP and project
our data set so that that's all
ready to go for us.
Now that we're done setting up, let's take
a look at expansion with
generated answers and there's a
reference here to the paper which demonstrates
some of the
empirical results that you can get
by applying this method.
So to do expansion
with generated answers we're
going to use an LLM, in
this case GPT, and
just the same as last time we're going
to prompt the model in
a particular way.
Let's create this function
called augment query
generated and we're going
to pass in a query, we're also going
to pass in a model argument, in this
case GPT 3.5 turbo by default,
and we're going to prompt the
model and in the system prompt
we're going to say you're a
helpful expert financial research assistant, provide an example
answer to the given
question that might be found in
a document, like an annual report.
In other words, we're
pretty much asking the
model to hallucinate, but we're gonna
use that hallucination for
something useful.
And in the user prompt, we're
just gonna pass the query as the content.
And then we'll do
our usual unpacking of
the response.
And that defines how we're
going to prompt our model.
Let's wire this together.
Here's our original query, asking
was there a
significant turnover in
the executive team.
We will generate a
hypothetical answer and then we'll
create our joint query which is
basically the original
query prepending the
hypothetical answer.
Now let's take a look at
what this actually looks
like after we generate it.
So here we see the output.
We see our original query,
was there a significant
turnover in the executive team,
and a hypothetical answer.
In the past fiscal
year there was no
significant turnover in the
executive team, the core members of
the executive team remained
unchanged, etc.
So let's send this query plus
the hypothetical critical response
to our retrieval system
as a query.
And we'll query the Chroma Collection
the usual way and
print out our results.
And we're sending the joint query
as the query to
our retrieval system. And we're retrieving
the documents and the
embeddings together. So these
are the documents that we get.
Back, we see things
here discussing leadership.
We see how consultants
and directors work together.
Here we have an
overview of the different
directors that we had in Microsoft.
And we talk about
the different board committees. Let's
visualize this. Let's see
what sort of difference this made.
So, to do that,
we get our retrieved embeddings,
we get the embedding
for our original query,
for our joint query,
and then we project all three.
I'm plotting the projection.
And we see the red
X is our original query,
the orange X is our
new query with the hypothetical
answer. And we see that we
get this nice cluster of results,
but most importantly, what I want
to illustrate here is that using
the hypothetical answer
moves our query elsewhere in space,
hopefully producing better
results for us.
So that was query
expansion with generated queries,
but there's another type of query expansion
we can also try. This
is called query expansion
with multiple queries. And
the way that you use this is to
use the LLM to
generate additional queries that
might help answering the
question. So what you do here is
you take your original query, you
pass it to the LLM, you ask the. LLM
to generate several new
related queries to the
same original query, and
then you pass those
new queries along with
your original query to
the vector database or
your retrieval system. That
gives you results for the original
and the new queries, and
then you pass all of
those results to the LLM
to complete the RAG loop.
So let's take a look at how
this works in practice.
Once again, the starting point is
a prompt in the model,
and we see here that
we have a system prompt,
and the system prompt is
a bit more detailed this time.
We take in a query,
which is our original query,
and we ask the model. It's
a helpful expert
financial research assistant. The
users are asking questions
about an annual report, so
this gives the model enough context
to know what sorts of queries
to generate. And
then you say, suggest up to five
additional related questions
to help them find the information
they need for
the provided question. Suggest
only short questions
without compound sentences,
and this makes sure that
we get simple queries.
Suggest a variety of
questions that cover different
aspects of the topic, and this is
very important because
there are many ways to rephrase
the same query, but what we're
actually asking for is
different but related queries.
And finally,
we want to make sure that they're
complete questions, they're related
to the original question, and we
ask some formatting output.
One important thing
to understand about
these techniques in
particular that bring an LLM into
the loop of retrieval is prompt
engineering becomes a concern. It's
something that you have
to think about and
I really recommend that
you as a student
play with these prompts
once you have a
chance to try the lab.
See how they may change,
see what different types
of queries you can
get the models to generate,
try different models,
and basically experiment,
not just with the retrieval system,
but with the prompts you're
using to augment your queries.
So let's
define this function and let's see
what we get when we
actually try this. So here's our original
query.
What were the most
important factors that contributed
to increases in revenue?
So this is a compound query.
There could be many,
many different factors and it's
not just about revenue.
And let's see what augmented queries
we get back.
We'll ask the model and let's print
a set of augmented
queries as output.
Great, so we got a few back.
We see that what were the
most important factors
that contributed to
decreases in revenue?
Great question.
What were the sources of revenue?
Also very important.
How were sales
and revenue distributed
across the different product lines?
Were there any changes in pricing
strategy?
Did the company acquire any new
customers? So you can see
that these are related
questions to our original query,
but they're not precisely the same and
they have different meanings. That's
very, very useful, and that's a great
illustration of augmenting
an original query
through query expansion
with multiple queries.
So let's see how this
works in practice once
we pass these queries
to our retrieval system.
So first,
we build our set of queries. Now,
Chroma can handle
multiple queries in parallel.
So what we're doing here is taking
our original query in
an array and then
concatenating that with our
array of augmented queries. So
now we have one array where
each entry is a query, our
original query, plus
the augmented queries.
And we can grab the results.
And again,
Chroma can do querying in batches.
And let's look at the retrieved
documents that we get.
And one thing that's
important here is because
the queries are related, you
might get the same
document retrieved for more
than one query. So what we need to
do is to deduplicate
the retrieved and that's what
we do here. And finally, let's just output
the documents that we get.
So we can see now the
documents that we get for each
query.
And these are all to do with revenue,
different aspects of revenue growth,
which is exactly what
we were hoping for.
We have increases in Windows revenue.
We can see things that
are coming from other components.
So for example, what were the most
important factors that contributed
to decreases in revenue?
So we see increased
sales and marketing expenses,
different types of investments,
different types of tax breaks.
Essentially, each of these
augmented queries are
providing us with
a slightly different set of results.
And let's visualize that. What
did we actually get
in geometric space in
response to these results?
So again, we'll take our original
query embedding and
our augmented query
embeddings and project them.
And the next thing we'll
do is project our result embeddings.
Before we do that,
we need to flatten the
list because we have a
list of embeddings per query.
We just want a
flat list of returned embeddings.
And then we just
project them as before.
And then let's
visualize what we get.
And we see that using query expansion,
we were able to
actually hit other related
parts of the data
set that our single
original query may not have reached.
And this gives us more
of a chance to find
all of the related information,
especially in the context
of more complex queries,
which require more
and different types
of information to answer.
So here we see that the
red X is our original query,
the orange X's are the augmented, the
new queries generated for
us by the LLM.
And then once again,
the green circles
represent the results
that we actually return by the
retrieval system to the model.
One way to think about this is that
a single query turns
into a single point
in embedding space.
And a single point
in embedding space likely doesn't
contain all of the
information that you need
to answer a more
complex query like this one. So
using this form of query expansion, where
we generate multiple related
queries using an LLM, gives
us a better chance
of capturing all of
the related information.
The downside of this, of course,
is now we have a lot
more results than we had originally.
And we're not sure if and which
of these results are actually
relevant to our query. In
the next lab, using cross-encoder re-ranking,
we have a
technique that allows us
to actually score the
relevancy of all the
returned results and use
only the ones we
feel match our original
query. And I'll demonstrate that in
the next lab. In this lab, I
recommend that you try playing around with
the query expansion prompts,
try your own queries,
and see the types of results you
get by asking different types of
questions about the
Microsoft Annual Report.